A Guide to the John S. and James L. Knight Foundation records, RG 5 Program Files, Subgroup Grant Files FA1795
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Community Partners Program, 1998-2012; 6; 20.89 Cubic Feet 55 letter document boxes
  - Long Beach Community Foundation, 20080068, 2008 June 9-2010 December 31 (Box 127, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 4843
    Long Beach Community Foundation, 20080068, $1,350,000 to position Long Beach Community Foundation as a civic leader by extending their management of Knight Foundation's community guidelines.
  - Miami Art Museum of Dade County Association (now Jorge M. Perez Art Museum), 20080238, 2008 December 16-2010 December 31 (Box 127, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 4844
    Miami Art Museum of Dade County Association (now Jorge M. Perez Art Museum of Miami Dade County Inc.), 20080238, $100,000, to support the Miami Art Museum with Board Development and Strategic Planning during their current transitional period of growth through an engagement with McKinsey and Co.
  - Community Action Partnership of Ramsey and Washington Counties, 20040170, 2004 September 14-2011 March 31 (Box 131, Folder 2-4)
    Knight File Number - 5009
    Grant 20040170, Community Action Partnership of Ramsey and Washington Counties, $2,625,000, to support a collaborative effort to provide a continuum of developmentally appropriate and culturally competent early childhood mental health services in Ramsey County. 2 folders.
  - Rutgers University Foundation, 20060183, 2006 December 4-2012 December 31 (Box 146, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 5170
    Grant 20060183, Rutgers University Foundation, $2,000,000, to construct the Knight Early Learning Research Academy in Camden, offering a collection of model services for improving early childhood education, raising the possibility the Academy will set the standard for early childhood education in New Jersey.
- Education, 1986-2004; 7; 23.17 Cubic Feet 61 letter document boxes
  - Mercer Univerisity, 86-152, 1986 December 19-1990 December 19 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 1437
    Grant 86-152, $250,000.00, as part of the $66.5 million Mercer University Sesquicentennial Campaign. This grant would be used to recognize Chester Albert Struby's contribution to Mercer and Central Georgia while serving the Macon Telegraph and News for 44 years. He joined the paper after graduating from Mercer in 1938.
  - Moore Community House Incorporated, 89-229, 1989 December 12-1990 December 12 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 1455
    Grant 89-229, $36,500.00, for STAR Tutors and Readers, an adult literacy project. The neighborhood in which Moore is located is home to "an ethnic mix of Vietnamese, blacks, and whites, and the city's highest concentration of poverty." The city's five largest housing projects where 669 families live are located here. 73% of these families earn less than $6,000 a year. STAR Tutors and Readers was begun in 1986 in the belief that improving literacy skills would improve the employability of neighborhood residents, strengthen their ability to participate more fully in society and strengthen family life.
  - Dade Public Education Fund, 89-165, 1989 September 22-1991 September 30 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Knight File Number - 1205
    Grant 89-165, $75,000.00, for programs to strengthen the public schools: teacher network, parent involvement, business involvement, realtor-school partnerships and conflict resolution training.
  - American Indian College Fund, 91-174, 1991 June 20-1992 June 20 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Knight File Number - 1163
    Grant 91-174, $150,000.00, for operating support. Organized by the presidents of 26 tribal colleges scatterd through 12 midwestern and western states, to unify their educational opportunity message and fund-raising activities.
  - Bellarmine College, 91-268, 1991 September 19-1992 September 19 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Knight File Number - 1172
    Grant 91-268, $237,000.00, for a challenge grant for Collegium, a comprehensive faculty development program. To support the continuing education of its faculty by sponsoring a faculty retreat, guest speakers, workshops on the skills of teaching, development of courses for team teaching, mentorships, and summer research.
  - Berea College, 89-268, 1989 December 12-1992 December 12 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    Knight File Number - 1174
    Grant 89-268, $250,000.00, for a challenge grant to implement an integrated library automation system to upgrade the quality of library and computer services.
  - Bethel College, 89-273, 1989 December 12-1992 December 12 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 1175
    Grant 89-273, $186,000.00, for a challenge grant to strengthen freshman retention including faculty/staff development, enhanced personal and academic support, and longitudinal study of student satisfaction.
  - Bibb County Public Schools, 91-264, 1991 September 19-1992 September 19 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 1176
    Grant 91-264, $100,000.00, for the High School Technology Project and related efforts to address the needs of at-risk students. By the introduction of technology-based instruction at the high school level.
  - Bucknell University, 91-269, 1991 September 19-1992 September 19 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 1178
    Grant 91-269, $250,000.00, for a challenge grant to support opportunities for student/faculty collaborations in the humanities, social science, and creative arts.
  - Charlotte-Mecklenburg Education Foundation, 91-375, 1991 December 12-1992 December 12 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    Knight File Number - 1185
    Grant 91-375, $100,000.00, to develop community support and to fund innovation and enrichment programs in the schools.
  - College Assistance Program (CAP) of Dade County, 91-105, 1991 June 20-1992 June 20 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    Knight File Number - 1193
    Grant 91-105, $25,000.00, to provide college scholarships for disadvantaged Dade County residents in the 1991-92 academic year and to establish the Knight Foundation Scholarship Fund.
  - Concordia College, 91-270, 1991 September 19-1992 September 19 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 1200
    Grant 91-270, $202,000.00, for a challenge grant to support a series of faculty development seminars focusing on third world cultures.
  - Drexel University, 91-126, 1991 June 20-1992 June 20 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 1212
    Grant 91-126, $30,000.00, to establish a permanent computer lab to support literacy outreach efforts.
  - Earlham College, 89-277, 1989 December 12-1992 December 31 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 1217
    Grant 89-277, $250,000.00, or a challenge grant to establish a program of grants to faculty/student teams for collaborative scholarly projects.
  - Florida International University Foundation, 91-139, 1991 June 20-1992 June 20 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    Knight File Number - 1225
    Grant 91-139, $25,000.00, for the second part of Living History: The Bay of Pigs Invasion, an oral/video history documentary.
  - Furman University, 89-269, 1989 December 12-1992 December 31 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    Knight File Number - 1228
    Grant 89-269, $250,000.00, for a challenge grant to strengthen efforts to recruit minority faculty and to provide professional development for junior faculty.
  - Gulfport School District, 91-118, 1991 June 20-1992 June 20 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    Knight File Number - 1236
    Grant 91-118, $20,000.00, for continuation and expansion of the Community Mentorship Program, a dropout prevention project.
  - Gustavus Adolphus College, 89-272, 1989 December 12-1992 December 31 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    Knight File Number - 1237
    Grant 89-272, $250,000, For a challenge grant to support innovative options for a faculty development program to include on-campus sabbaticals and short-term faculty exchanges and leaves, special mentoring of high-ability students, and faculty leadership development.
  - Hiram College, 91-272, 1991 September 19-1992 September 19 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    Knight File Number - 1239
    Grant 91-272, $250,000.00, for a challenge grant to support programs of the Center for International Awareness and Exchange.
  - IMPACT II - The Teachers Network, 91-324, 1991 December 12-1992 December 12 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 1241
    Grant 91-324, $50,000.00, for IMPACT II: The Teachers Network to develop "The Teachers Vision of the Future of Education: Creating the Models and Strategies for Implementation".
  - Kids Voting USA, 91-376, 1991 December 12-1992 December 12 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 1405
    Grant 91-376, $100,000.00, modeled after a program conducted for more than 30 years in Costa Rica, where voter participation is often 90 percent. K-12 students receive lessons in voting, discuss candidates and issues with their parents and then accompany their parents to polling places on election day. To expand this program, successfully pioneered in Arizona, to a maximum of 15 other states for 1992 elections, including four or more in which Knight Foundations cities are located.
  - Kids Voting USA, 92-1, 1991 December 12-1992 December 12 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 1406
    Grant 92-1, $38,000.00, to provide seed funding for Kids Voting activities in six Knight Foundation cities. Modeled after a program conducted for more than 30 years in Costa Rica, where voter participation is often 90 percent. K-12 students receive lessons in voting, discuss candidates and issues with their parents and then accompany their parents to polling places on election day.
  - Kids Voting USA, 92-2, 1991 December 12-1992 December 12 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 1408
    Grant 92-2, $137,000.00, to provide seed funding for Kids Voting activities in six Knight Foundation cities.
  - Lafayette College, 91-273, 1991 September 19-1992 September 19 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    Knight File Number - 1410
    Grant 91-73, $250,000.00, to support the professional development of junior faculty and expand student/faculty collaborations in the science and engineering.
  - La Salle University, 91-95, 1991 June 20-1992 June 20 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    Knight File Number - 1412
    Grant 91-95, $15,000.00, for the development of a Southeast Asian component within the bilingual/bicultural masters program.
  - Lees College Inc., 91-173, 1991 June 20-1992 June 20 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 1413
    Grant 91-173, $55,000.00, for continuation of the Educational Advancement Program benefiting students with low academic achievement.
  - Long Beach Unified School District, 91-40, 1991 March 26-1992 March 26 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 1423
    Grant 91-40, $27,643.00, for the purchase of trailer to house a Stop-N Center for personal counseling for students.
  - Los Altos School District, 91-367, 1991 December 12-1992 December 12 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 1424
    Grant 91-367, $75,000.00, to train elementary school teachers in the "Talking Fingers" method of computer-aided instruction in reading and writing.
  - Macon College, 91-79, 1991 March 26 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 1426
    Grant 91-79, $135,000.00, to support two collaborative projectsi n public education: The Bibb County College Counseling Program and the Teachers in Service Program.
  - Millsaps College, 91-274, 1991 September 19-1992 September 19 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    Knight File Number - 1450
    Grant 91-274, $250,000.00, a challenge grant for faculty development to support the implementation of a new core curriculum.
  - Moore Community House Incorporated, 91-262, 1991 September 19-1992 September 19 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    Knight File Number - 1456
    Grant 91-262, $30,000.00, for expasion of lthe adult literacy program. Now known as Literacy Volunteers of Biloxi, the program approaches literacy as a means for the personal empowerment of its students.
  - Museum of Science Inc., 91-167, 1991 June 20-1992 June 20 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    Knight File Number - 1469
    Grant 91-167, $25,000.00, to establish a science literacy fund which would support the following components: (1) a pre-Columbus exhibition; (2) continuation of owl and woodstork research; and (3) training modules for hands-on science programs, and (4) a quarterly education newsletter for Florida teachers.
  - Philadelphia High School Academies Inc., 91-186, 1991 September 19-1992 September 19 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    Knight File Number - 1814
    Grant 91-186, $50,000, for expansion of the Academies within the public schools.
  - Presbyterian College, 91-275, 1991 September 19-1992 September 19 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    Knight File Number - 1820
    Grant 91-275, $237,000, a challenge grant to establish a program of applied ethics.
  - Salem College, 89-278, 1989 December 12-1992 December 31 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    Knight File Number - 1713
    Grant 89-278, $250,000.00, a challenge grant for the Women's Achivement Initiative, a comprehensive student recruitment and retention program a response to invitational RFP for liberal arts colleges, Round 2.
  - Teach for America Inc., 91-69, 1991 March 26-1992 March 26 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 1257
    Grant 91-69, $150,000, for the recruitment, training, and placement of 135 Teacher Corps members who will teach in Miami and Long Beach, California. (Teach for America assembles a corps of individuals who believe that all children can learn and who will be effective teachers for at least two years while filling positions that districts would not otherwise be able to fill with certified, qualified teachers.)
  - Tougaloo College, 91-279, 1991 September 19-1992 September 19 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 1748
    Grant 91-279, $100,000.00, for a Presidential Leadership grant.
  - United States Peace Corps, 91-306, 1991 December 12-1992 December 12 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    Knight File Number - 1751
    Grant 91-306, $331,663.00, for the Peace Corps Fellows/USA Program which prepares and places returning volunteers as public school teachers and to benefit the following colleges and universities in proximity to Knight cities of interest: Florida International University ($40,000), Georgia College (76,775), San Francisco State University ($35,000), Temple University ($73,314), University of Michigan - Ann Arbor ($50,000), University of Southern California ($8,646), and to the University of Southern Mississippi ($47,928).
  - University of North Carolina at Charlotte, 91-234, 1991 September 19-1992 September 19 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    Knight File Number - 2012
    Grant 91-234, $52,000.00, for the North Carolina Atlas, a book of information about North Carolina for policy makers, students and the general public.
  - Valparaiso University Association Inc., 91-276, 1991 September 19-1992 September 19 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    Knight File Number - 1772
    Grant 91-276, $250,000, a challenge grant to increase the diversity of the faculty, student body and curriculum.
  - Baldwin County School District, 92-210, 1992 September 16-1993 September 16 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 1168
    Grant 92-210, $20,000.00, for an innovative program for developing the leadership skills of key administrators to help enhance the capacity of local school administrators to lead education reform.
  - Baskervill Ministries Inc., 92-314, 1992 December 15-1993 December 15 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 1171
    Grant 92-314, $30,000.00, For the Holy Cross-Faith Memorial School of Pawley's Island, a distinctive local institution with a heritage of service to African-American children.
  - California State University, Dominguez Hills, 92-335, 94-99, 1992 December 15-1993 December 15 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 1914
    Grant 92-335, 94-99 (supplement), $252,000.00, for expansion and evaluation of the Science, Technology Enrichment Program (STEP), for middle school students, in cooperation with the Compton School District. Merged with 94-99, to supplement a 1992 Excellence in Education grant with travel funds for the AAHE school/College Conference in 1994 and 1995.
  - Central Piedmont Community College Foundation, 92-337, 1992 December 15-1993 December 15 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    Knight File Number - 1183
    Grant 92-337, $251,000.00, for support of the collaborative mathematical pathways project involving the Central Piedmont Community College, University of North Carolina at Charlotte and the Charlotte-Mecklenburg Schools.
  - Centre College of Kentucky, 89-72, 1989 March 21-1993 March 21 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    Knight File Number - 1184
    Grant 89-72, $180,000.00, for a challenge grant to increase collaborative academic activities between faculty and students.
  - Coastal Educational Foundation Incorporated, 92-127, 1992 June 17-1993 June 17 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    Knight File Number - 1192
    Grant 92-127, $30,000.00, to promote coordinated planning for Horry County through community consensus forums.
  - Columbia College, 92-342, 1992 December 15-1993 December 15 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 1196
    Grant 92-342, $252,000.00, To establish "schools as centers of the community" designed to centralize provision of educational, social, health and community services.
  - Communities in Schools, Inc., 92-13, 1992 March 25-1993 March 25 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 1198
    Grant 92-13, $300,000.00. To provide training and technical assistance to expand national, regional and state networks for dropout prevention.
  - Dade Public Education Fund, 92-80, 1992 June 17-1993 June 17 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 1206
    Grant 92-80, $50,000.00, for continuation of Impact II, a teacher networking and dissemination program.
  - Dade Women's Welfare Coalition, 92-246, 1992 December 15-1993 December 15 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 1210
    Grant 92-246, $33,000.00, for TROY (Teaching & Rehabilitating Our Youth) to develop a state-of-the-art curriculum at Langston Hughes Academy, a new alternative school for high-risk, inner-city youth.
  - Florida State University, 92-336, 1992 December 15-1993 December 15 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    Knight File Number - 1350
    Grant 92-336, $252,000.00, to be used over three years for collaboration with a local middle school to develop TEAMS (Technology Enhancing Achievement in the Middle Schools) a model, technology-based curriculum emphasizing integrative, interactive learning.
  - Friends University, 92-64, 1992 June 17-1993 June 17 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    Knight File Number - 1227
    Grant 92-64, $55,000.00, to improve the university's capacity to retain students and to mentor minority students.
  - Galef Institute, 92-170, 1992 September 16-1993 September 16 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 1230
    Grant 92-170, $35,000.00, for an interdisciplinary curriculum for grades K-8 and a professional development program for teachers known collectively as "Different Ways of Knowing", a pilot program in the Compton Unified School District, to address the needs of at-risk children through applied research.
  - Grand Forks Public School District, 92-28, 1992 March 25-1993 March 25 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 1233
    Grant 92-28, $51,800.00, for Literacy Connections, a parent/school cooperative program encouraging children to read.
  - Hampshire College, 92-343, 1992 December 15-1993 December 15 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 1369
    Grant 92-343, $179,000.00, for a summer program to address academic failure and school alienation among students, and the professional development of middle school teachers.
  - IMPACT II - The Teachers Network, 92-252, 1992 December 15-1993 December 15 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 1240
    Grant 92-252, $150,000.00, to document and disseminate models of school reform developed by this national teachers' network.
  - Juanita College, 92-340, 1992 December 15-1993 December 15 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    Knight File Number - 1399
    Grant 92-340, $252,000.00, to expand its successful Chemistry in Motion outreach to area high schools to include biology and junior high schools.
  - Kalamazoo College, 89-73, 1989 March 21-1993 March 21 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    Knight File Number - 1401
    Grant 89-73, $250,000.00, to support the development of a more comprehensive effort to recruit and retain minority students. Kalamazoo College is one of eight leading private liberal arts colleges selected to receive initial grants in the Foundation's "Excellence in Undergraduate Education" program.
  - Kent State University Foundation Inc., 92-19, 1992 March 25-1993 March 25 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    Knight File Number - 1404
    Grant 92-19, $12,500.00, for the capital campaign to construct new facilities for WKSU-FM Public Radio Station.
  - Kids Voting USA, 92-151, 1992 June 17-1993 June 17 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    Knight File Number - 1407
    Grant 92-151, $100,000.00, for additional operating support, for Kids Voting USA a nonpartisan, grassroots voter education program focussed on school children.
  - Literary Volunteers of America, 92-99, 1992 June 17-1993 June 17 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    Knight File Number - 1416
    Grant 92-99, $34,975.00, for Literary Links, a method of literacy instruction that permits tutors to instruct two or three students as a group.
  - Moore Community House Incorporated, 92-253, 1992 December 15-1993 December 15 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 1462
    Grant 92-253, $31,290.00, for an adult education center to hire an additional literacy instructor and support student council activities. Moore House is a highly regarded social service agency located in a poor, multi-racial section of Biloxi where drop-out, unemployment and illiteracy rates are high.
  - Oakland Literacy Council, 92-183, 1992 September 16-1993 September 16 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 1804
    Grant 92-183, $99,000, to expand basic literacy instruction for adults.
  - Teach for America Inc., 92-48, 1992 March 25-1993 March 25 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    Knight File Number - 1263
    Grant 92-48, $750,000, for short-term operating support to encourage the development of a diversified, long-term funding base. (Teach for America assembles a corps of individuals who believe that all children can learn and who will be effective teachers for at least two years while filling positions that districts would not otherwise be able to fill with certified, qualified teachers.)
  - San Jose Conservation Corps, 92-47, 1992 March 25-1993 March 25 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 1715
    Grant 92-47, $20,000.00, to develop and test culturally sensitive instructional software.
  - San Jose State University Foundation, 92-40, 1992 March 25-1993 March 25 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 1717
    Grant 92-40, $115,417.00, for LEAPartnership/San Jose Artists in Schools Residency Program. The program brings accomplished artists from a wide range of disciplines and teachers together to plan and conduct classroom art activities.
  - San Jose State University Foundation, 92-154, 1992 June 17-1993 June 17 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 1716
    Grant 92-154, $75,000.00, for a scholarship incentive program designed to encourage students to complete high school and pursue higher education.
  - University of Pennsylvania, 92-251, 1992 December 15-1993 December 15 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 1771
    Grant 92-251, $80,000, for the center for Greater Philadelphia to expand its efforts to promote regional cooperation in Southeast Pennsylvania.
  - Allegheny College, 90-225, 1990 September 27-1994 September 27 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 1161
    Grant 90-225, $250,000.00, for a challenge grant to support two faculty development programs essential to implementation of the new college-wide curriculum in response to invitational RFP for liberal arts colleges, Round 3.